It’s 1526 in what is now Northern India,
سال ۱۵۲۶ در شمال هند امروزی است،
and Sultan Ibrahim Lodhi is about to face off against a prince
سلطان ابراهیم لودی در آستانه رویارویی با شاهزاده‌ای
from Central Asia, Zahiruddin Muhammad Babur.
از آسیای مرکزی به نام ظهیرالدین مُحمَّد بابُر است.
To quash the threat, the Sultan brings his war elephants to battle.
سلطان برای سرکوب این تهدید، فیل‌های جنگی خود را به نبرد می‌آورد.
But it’s said that the explosions of Babur’s cannons and muskets
اما گفته می‌شود که انفجار توپ‌ها و صدای شلیک تفنگ فتیله‌ای لشکر بابر،
startled the elephants and they trampled the Sultan’s own army.
فیل‌ها را وحشت‌زده کرد و آن‌ها لشکر خود سلطان را لگدمال کردند.
Babur had long harbored ambitions of building his own empire.
بابر از دیرباز آرزوی ساختن امپراتوری خود را در سر داشت.
Though he was descended from some of the world’s most successful conquerors,
اگرچه او از نوادگان برخی از موفق‌ترین فاتحان جهان بود،
he struggled to gain a foothold
اما برای به دست آوردن جایگاهی
among the many ambitious princes in Central Asia.
در میان بسیاری از شاهزادگان جاه‌طلب در آسیای مرکزی تلاش کرد.
So he turned his attention to India,
در نتیجه او توجه خود را به هند معطوف کرد،
where his descendants stayed and built the Mughal Empire,
جایی که فرزندانش در آنجا ماندند و امپراتوری مغول را ساختند،
one of the wealthiest and most powerful states in the early modern world
یکی از ثروتمندترین و قدرتمندترین قلمروهای اوایل دنیای مدرن
and home to nearly a quarter of the global population.
و خانه‌ی تقریباً یک‌چهارم جمعیت جهان.
Babur died just four years after that fateful battle,
بابر تنها چهار سال پس از آن نبرد سرنوشت‌ساز درگذشت،
but his own memoirs and the work of his descendants
اما خاطرات خودش و کارهای نوادگانش
immortalized him in colorful fashion.
او را به شکلی سرزنده جاودانه کرد.
His daughter, Gulbadan, recalled in her own memoir how Babur—
دختر او، گل‌بدن، در خاطرات خود به یاد می‌آورد که چگونه بابر -
having recently given up drinking—
که اخیراً مشروب را کنار گذاشته بود -
filled a newly-constructed pool with lemonade rather than wine.
استخری را که تازه ساخته بود به جای شراب، با شربت آبلیمو پر کرد.
His grandson, Akbar, commissioned exquisite miniature paintings
نوه‌اش، اکبر، نقاشی‌های مینیاتوری نفیسی
of Babur’s stories—
از داستان‌های بابر سفارش داد -
one depicted the empire’s founder riding through his camp,
یکی از آن‌ها بنیانگذار امپراتوری را حین اسب‌سواری به اردوگاهش نشان می‌داد
drunkenly slumped over his horse.
که مستانه روی اسبش لمیده بود.
It was Akbar who consolidated Mughal power.
این اکبر بود که قدرت مغول را تثبیت کرد.
He established protections for peasants—
او تمهیدات حمایتی برای دهقانان ایجاد کرد -
which in turn increased their productivity and generated more tax revenue—
که به نوبه خود بهره‌وری آنها را افزایش داد و درآمد مالیاتی بیشتری ایجاد کرد -
and embarked on military campaigns to expand Mughal territory.
و لشکرکشی را برای گسترش قلمرو مغول آغاز کرد.
Princes who swore allegiance to him were rewarded,
شاهزادگانی که با او بیعت می‌کردند پاداش می‌گرفتند،
while he made brutal examples of those who resisted,
در حالی که او نمونه‌های وحشیانه‌ای از مخالفان،
killing them and many of their subjects.
کشتار آن‌ها و بسیاری از رعیت‌هایشان می‌ساخت.
His conquests opened access to port cities on the Indian Ocean,
فتوحات او دسترسی به شهرهای بندری در اقیانوس هند را باز کرد
which connected the Mughals to Arab, Chinese, Ottoman, and European traders,
که مغول‌ها را به بازرگانان عرب، چینی، عثمانی و اروپایی متصل می‌کرد
bringing in incalculable wealth,
و ثروت غیرقابل محاسبه،
including silver and new crops from the Americas.
از جمله نقره و محصولات جدید را از قاره آمریکا به ارمغان می‌آورد.
As the Muslim ruler of a diverse, multiethnic empire,
به عنوان حاکم امپراتوری مسلمان، متنوع و چند قومیتی،
Akbar worked to create internal cohesion by appointing members
اکبر برای ایجاد انسجام داخلی
of the Hindu majority to high positions in his government,
با انتصاب اعضای اکثریت هندو به مناصب عالی در دولت خود،
marrying a Hindu bride,
ازدواج با عروسی هندو
and distributing translated copies of the “Mahabharata,”
و توزیع نسخه‌های ترجمه‌شده «مهابهاراتا»،
an ancient Indian epic poem, to his Muslim nobles.
شعر باستانی حماسی هند، برای اشراف مسلمانش تلاش کرد.
Akbar also hosted lively religious debates where Sunni and Shia Muslims,
او میزبان مناظرات مذهبی پرجنب‌وجوشی نیز بود که در آن مسلمانان سنی و شیعه،
Hindus, Jains, Zoroastrians,
هندوها، جین‌ها، زرتشتیان
and the newly arrived Portuguese Jesuit missionaries
و مبلغان تازه‌وارد پرتغالی یسوعی
defended the merits of their respective faiths.
از شایستگی‌های مذهب‌هایشان دفاع کردند.
While most participants viewed this as an intellectual exercise,
در حالی که اکثر شرکت‌کنندگان این کار را یک تمرین فکری می‌دانستند،
Portuguese missionaries were disappointed by their failure to convert Akbar.
مبلغان پرتغالی از شکست خود در تغییر دین اکبر ناامید شدند.
The Mughals built architectural masterpieces
مغول‌ها شاهکارهای معماری
such as the Taj Mahal and the Red Fort,
مانند تاج محل و قلعه سرخ را ساختند،
a palace three kilometers around, that housed 50,000 people
کاخی در محوطه سه کیلومتری که ۵۰,۰۰۰ نفر را در خود جای داده بود
and contained the magnificent gold and jewel-encrusted Peacock Throne.
و تخت طاووس باشکوه از طلا و جواهرات تزئین‌شده را در خود گنجانده بود.
Just the throne took seven years to construct.
ساخت فقط تاج و تخت هفت سال طول کشید.
During its first 180 years, the Mughals had only six rulers,
در طول ۱۸۰ سال اول، مغول‌ها تنها شش فرمانروا داشتند
which contributed to the empire’s stability.
که به استحکام امپراتوری کمک کرد.
When the fourth emperor, Jahangir,
هنگامی که چهارمین امپراتور، جهانگیر،
struggled with alcohol and opioid addiction,
با اعتیاد به الکل و مواد افیونی دست و پنجه نرم می‌کرد،
his wife, Nur Jahan, took the reins as co-ruler.
همسرش، نور جهان، فرمانروایی را به دست گرفت.
When a traitorous general captured her husband in an attempted coup,
هنگامی که یک ژنرال خیانتکار شوهرش را در یک کودتا دستگیر کرد،
she negotiated his release and rallied the army to stop the rebellion.
او برای آزادی شوهرش، مذاکره و ارتش را برای متوقف کردن شورش جمع کرد.
She once led a hunting party to track down a tiger that was terrorizing a village,
او یک بار مهمانی شکاری را برای ردیابی ببری که عامل وحشت دهکده‌ای بود، رهبری کرد
leading one poet to write:
و منجر به سرودن این شعر شد:
“Though Nur Jahan be in form of a woman/ In the ranks of men she’s a tiger-slayer.”
«اگرچه نور جهان به شکل یک زن باشد/ در ردیف مردان او یک ببرکش است»
Following the death of the sixth emperor, Aurangzeb, in 1707,
پس از مرگ ششمین امپراتور، اورنگ زیب، در سال ۱۷۰۷،
seven emperors took the throne over the next 21 years.
هفت امپراتور طی ۲۱ سال بعد تاج و تخت را به دست گرفتند.
These frequent transitions of power reflected
این انتقال مکرر قدرت بازتاب‌دهنده بحران‌های سیاسی،
the larger political, economic, social, and environmental crises
اقتصادی، اجتماعی و زیست محیطی بزرگتری بود
that plagued the empire throughout the 18th century.
که امپراتوری را در طول قرن هجدهم گرفتار کرده بود.
In response to this turmoil,
در پاسخ به این آشفتگی،
regional leaders started refusing to pay taxes and broke away from Mughal control.
رهبران منطقه شروع به امتناع از پرداخت مالیات کردند و از سلطه مغول خارج شدند.
The British East India Company offered military support to these regional rulers,
شرکت بریتانیایی هند شرقی از این حاکمان منطقه حمایت نظامی کرد
which in turn increased the company's political influence,
که به نوبه خود نفوذ سیاسی شرکت را افزایش داد
enabling it to eventually take direct control of Bengal,
و این امکان را به آن داد تا در نهایت کنترل مستقیم بنگال،
one of the wealthiest regions in India.
یکی از ثروتمندترین مناطق هند را در دست بگیرد.
By the 19th century, the East India Company had massive political influence
در قرن نوزدهم، شرکت هند شرقی دارای نفوذ سیاسی گسترده
and a large standing army, which included Indian troops.
و ارتش ثابت بزرگی بود که شامل نیروهای هندی نیز می‌شد.
When these troops revolted in 1857,
هنگامی که این نیروها در سال ۱۸۵۷
aiming to force out the British and restore Mughal influence,
با هدف بیرون راندن بریتانیا و بازگرداندن نفوذ مغول شورش کردند،
the British government intervened,
دولت بریتانیا مداخله کرد.
replacing company rule with direct colonial rule,
و حکومت شرکت را با حکومت مستعمره مستقیم جایگزین کرد،
deposing the last Mughal emperor and sending him into exile.
آخرین امپراتور مغول را خلع کرد و او را به تبعید فرستاد.
And so, over three centuries after its founding,
و بدین ترتیب، بیش از سه قرن پس از تأسیس،
the Mughal Empire came to an end.
امپراتوری مغول به پایان رسید.